Preliminary Guide to the Edward Tallmadge Root Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Edward Tallmadge Root family papers
1804-1948
1874-1948
MS 1248
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
3.5
(4 boxes)
Correspondence, diaries, sermons, essays, speeches, and printed matter relating to E. Tallmadge Root's service as a Congregational minister in churches in New England, 1890-1935. Included also are speeches made in connection with his candidacy in Massachusetts for governor (1940) and Senator (1944) for the Prohibition Party. Personal papers include autograph albums, family account books, scrapbooks, and miscellaneous family correspondence. One-third of the papers consist of diaries kept by E. Tallmadge Root from 1874 to 1948; by William Scott Root from 1874 to 1880; and by other family members from 1842 to 1899.
Root, Edward Tallmadge, 1865-1948
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Dorothy C. Root, 1981 and 1983.
Biographical / Historical
Edward Tallmadge Root: clergyman; graduate, N.Y. Classical Institute, 1883; A.B., Yale, 1887, B.D., 1890; ordained to the ministry of the Presbyterian Church, 1890; pastor, Second Congregational Church, Baltimore, 1891-1896, Elmwood Temple Congregational Church, Providence, 1896-1904; secretary, R.I. Federation of Churches, 1903-1912, Mass. Federation of Churches, 1904-1930; pastor, Congregational Church, Westmore, Vermont, 1933-1935; prohibition candidate for governor, 1940, for U.S. Senator, 1944.
Scope and Contents
Correspondence, diaries, sermons, essays, speeches, and printed matter relating to E. Tallmadge Root's service as a Congregational minister in churches in New England, 1890-1935. Included also are speeches made in connection with his candidacy in Massachusetts for governor (1940) and Senator (1944) for the Prohibition Party. Personal papers include autograph albums, family account books, scrapbooks, and miscellaneous family correspondence. One-third of the papers consist of diaries kept by E. Tallmadge Root from 1874 to 1948; by William Scott Root from 1874 to 1880; and by other family members from 1842 to 1899.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research.
Families; Massachusetts -- Politics and government; Autographs; Sermons; Diaries; Clergy; Root, Edward Tallmadge, 1865-1948; Root, William Scott; Tallmadge, Samuel, 1755-1825; Root family; Congregational Churches in the United States; Prohibition Party
- Inventory, 1804--1948
  - E. Tallmadge Root (1865-1948)
    - Unsorted correspondence (9 folders) (Box 1)
    - Sermons and speeches (3 folders), 1894-1947 (Box 1)
    - Programs of meetings he addressed (Box 1)
    - Books and pamphlets (Box 1)
    - Printed material (Box 1)
    - Manuscripts and typescripts (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - Pamphlets and papers relating to church(es) (Box 1)
    - Church programs and announcements (Box 1)
    - Papers relating to church timber lands, 1934-1935 (Box 1)
    - Genealogy (Box 1)
    - Notes (Box 1)
    - Materials relating to Yale (Box 1)
    - Calling cards (Box 1)
    - Unsorted newspaper clippings (5 folders) (Box 1)
    - Our Young Folks: An Illustrated Magazine for Boys and Girls, 1873 (Box 2)
    - Autograph book, notebook (Box 2)
    - Family expense books, 1884-1945 (Box 2)
    - New Testament, 1804 (Box 2)
    - Scrapbook of published poems (Box 2)
    - Scrapbook of articles (Box 2)
  - Letters to Mary T. Root (2 folders), 1890-1895 (Box 2)
  - Samuel Tallmadge, unsorted correspondence, 1815-1867 (Box 2)
  - Journals and Diaries
    - Journal, including section titled "Observations on Development of My Son, Edward Merrill Root" (Box 2)
    - Journals of E. Tallmadge Root and W. Scott Root, 1874-1887 (Box 3)
    - Journal of E. Tallmadge Root, 1874-1891 (Box 3)
    - Journal, unidentified, 1842-1888 (Box 3)
    - Diaries of others, 1865-1899 (Box 3)
    - Diaries of William Scott Root, 1874-1880 (Box 3)
    - Diaries of E. Tallmadge Root (10 folders), 1874-1948 (Box 3)
  - DAR certificate for Georgiana M. Root (in mailing tube), 1922 (Box 3)
- Additional Material, 1882-1947; Accession 1984-M-006
  - Correspondence
    - To ET
      - Bates, William, 1915 January 15 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Merrill, 1928, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Post Cards, 1894-1947 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Winthrop, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - To Merrill
      - Unidentified, 1917 April 23 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - From Alsa
      - Family, 1927, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - From Merrill
      - Family, 1930, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - General, 1882-1941 (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
      - Handwritten Conversation with Lord Bryon, Undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Photograph (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Poems by ET (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Programs, clippings (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Unidentified typescript of letter and questionnaire, Undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Account books, 1903, 1928, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - 50th Anniversary of City of Somerville (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - Guest book (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - Personal index book (Box 1, Folder 18)